Guide to the New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health (NYCOSH) Records WAG.029
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health (NYCOSH) Records
1971-2024
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health
WAG.029
62.5 Linear Feet in 61 record cartons, 2 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize flat box, and 2 folders in shared housing
4 websites in 4 archived websites.
3 16mm_film_reels
The New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health (NYCOSH) was founded in 1976 to advocate for safe and healthy workplaces. NYCOSH bases much of its advocacy on the Occupational Safety and Health Act of 1970 and has helped spearhead successful efforts to preserve the Federal Occupational Safety and Health Administration (OSHA). The collection includes minutes of membership, steering committee, health and technical committee, personnel committee, political education committee and workers' compensation committee meetings, general correspondence, requests for assistance, membership records, course materials, publicity flyers, fact sheets, newsletters, fund raising materials, pamphlets, lobbying materials, websites, and educational materials.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into four series:
Series I: Management, 1977-1989
Series II: Activities, 1979-1987
Subseries A: The Committee to Save OSHA, 1979-1983
Subseries B: NYCOSH (New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health) Conferences, 1980-1986
Subseries C: Health and Safety Activities and Information, 1981-1987
Series III: Unprocessed Material, 1971-2011
Series IV: Archived Websites
Series I is arranged by function and then alphabetically. Series II is arranged by activity and then by date. Series III has not been arranged by an archivist.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical Note
The New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health (NYCOSH) was founded in 1976 to advocate for safe and healthy workplaces. NYCOSH bases much of its advocacy on the Occupational Safety and Health Act of 1970 and has helped spearhead successful efforts to preserve the Federal Occupational Safety and Health Administration (OSHA).
The Occupational Safety and Health Act of 1970 established rules and regulations governing health and safety standards in American workplaces. In the mid-seventies, the Federal Occupational Safety and Health Administration (OSHA) funded several educational programs under the auspices of Cornell University's Labor Studies Program. These programs increased health and safety consciousness among health care professionals. Out of these programs, a group of individuals organized NYCOSH in 1976 as an independent organization to advocate safe and healthy workplaces. NYCOSH's began as a strictly volunteer organization which solicited membership from labor unions and individuals. Initially, NYCOSH's budget consisted of funds collected in member dues. Eventually, NYCOSH began supplementing its budget with grant monies from city, state, and federal offices as well as private foundation grants.
The steering committee represented the central body around which NYCOSH worked, with a number of single issue committees designed to address specific topics faced by members. The committees included the health and technical, reproductive rights, workers' compensation, and political education. The most active of these committees were the health and technical, workers' compensation, and political education committees. The health and technical committee collected information regarding health and safety issues for a variety of occupations and organized educational forums, fact sheets, pamphlets, and other tools designed to inform workers of potential health and safety risks associated with their jobs. The workers' compensation committee helped individuals in their pursuit of compensation for injuries and illness resulting from their work. The committee produced a pamphlet describing all of the steps necessary for successful completion of workers' compensation disputes. The committee also drafted and lobbied for strong workers' compensation legislation at all governmental levels. The political education committee lead most of NYCOSH's lobbying initiatives, including regulations for saving OSHA legislation, asbestos, and right to know laws.
NYCOSH provided four basic services for its members, technical support, educational services, political education, and a task force addressing the special needs of minority workers.
Ronald Reagan's election in 1980, represented a serious threat to OSHA legislation. Numerous other COSH organizations, environmental organizations, and other politically oriented groups, and unions, joined NYCOSH forming a national coalition to fight attempts to weaken OSHA legislation. NYCOSH played a major role coordinating what would become the Committee to Save OSHA and efforts to persuade federal officials, senators and congressmen that OSHA must be maintained as it was and, in the future, strengthened. For the duration of the Reagan Administration, NYCOSH would reinstate the coalition to address threats to the legislation. Other topics that NYCOSH addressed in the 1980s included toxic substances and reproductive hazards and attempts to regulate women's work based on these issues. NYCOSH published its first reproductive hazard curriculum in 1980. Asbestos hazards became a major concern for the organization also. The health hazards workers and communities faced from asbestos remains a central issue in NYCOSH organizing. The first of a number of conferences addressing the issues related to asbestos hazards was staged in 1980.
In 1981, NYCOSH busied itself with a large number of conferences and activities. The growth of the organization demanded that it hire a full-time and part-time staff person to facilitate its services and activities. Joel Shufro, a board member, became the executive director of the organization, and continues to lead NYCOSH. Over the course of the year, NYCOSH held several conferences on topics such as toxic substances, hazardous wastes, and workers' "right to know." Work also began on a major conference devoted to the problems of minority workers called the Harlem Occupational Health Conference and on one about hazards in the office. Legislation which NYCOSH began working on in 1981 included the asbestos compensation, longshore and harbors workers' compensation and New York State workers' compensation bills. Legislative lobbying for occupational safety and health continued to be one of NYCOSH's major functions. In 1982 the longshore and harbors workers' legislation passed even though NYCOSH and other organizations lobbied strongly against it.
In 1984, because of major lobbying efforts by NYCOSH, the New York State Senate established the Committee on Occupational Health and Safety. NYCOSH also organized all of its fact sheets and published a list of publications it produced and made available to the public. Part of this organizing effort resulted in a resource guide and a library for membership and public use. This year also began NYCOSH's work to pass an asbestos control law in New York City. This effort was successful in 1986 with the passage of the law.
NYCOSH's worked continued with the Asbestos Task Force and video display terminal (VDT), right to know, and workers' compensation issues at the forefront of its efforts. These efforts culminated in 1988 with the passage of the asbestos control legislation in New York City, the NYC Community Right to Know law, and the nation's first VDT law passed in Suffolk County. In 1989, NYCOSH's lobbying efforts passed the Workers' Compensation Reform bill in New York State.
Recently, NYCOSH has been involved in the struggle to gain medical screening and care for 9/11's first responders and cleanup workers. NYCOSH's longtime Executive Director, Joel Shufro, retired in 2014.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health, 1985. The accession number associated with this gift is 1985.009. Additional donations were made in 2005 and 2009. The accession number associated with these materials is 2011.075.
Two additional donations, comprising the materials in Boxes 57-59, were made in 2012. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 2012.015 and 2012.023.
Another two additional donations, comprising the materials in Boxes 60-63, were made in 2014. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 2014.010 and 2014.016. Three pamphlets related to workplace safety were also donated in 2014. The accession number associated with these items is 2014.137.
Board Minutes from 2012 - 2013 donated by the NYCOSH, 2016. The accession number associated with this gift is 2016.006
http://nycosh.org/ was initially selected by curators and captured through the use of The California Digital Library's Web Archiving Service in 2007 as part of the Labor Unions and Organizations (U.S.) Web Archive. In 2015, this website was migrated to Archive-It. Archive-It uses web crawling technology to capture websites at a scheduled time and displays only an archived copy, from the resulting WARC file, of the website. In 2021, https://twitter.com/NYCOSH/ was added. The accession number associated with this website is 2021.010. In May 2022, https://nyhealthynails.org/ was added. The accession number associated with this website is 2022.060. In October 2024, https://x.com/NYCOSH/ was added. The accession number associated with this website is 2024.060.
In April 2025, Joel Shufro, NYCOSH Executive Director, donated two pamphlets; the accession number associated with this accretion is 2025.046. Shufro donated an accretion of press releases and reports in June 2025; the accession number associated with this accretion is 2025.061.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to some audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes minutes of membership, steering committee, health and technical committee, personnel committee, political education committee and workers' compensation committee meetings, general correspondence, requests for assistance, membership records, course materials, publicity flyers, fact sheets, newsletters, fund raising materials, pamphlets, lobbying materials, websites, and educational materials. The collection includes a large amount of information regarding OSHA legislation and the lobbying effort made by NYCOSH in association with the national organization, the Committee to Save OSHA, against attempts to limit its regulatory reach in 1980. Another large section of the material covers NYCOSH activities regarding asbestos. These documents include material from two major conferences and campaigns lobbying for a New York City law controlling asbestos and other regulatory legislation at the state and federal levels.
The other documents constituting the bulk of this collection are correspondence. The correspondence includes lobbying material sent to political figures, form letters regarding dues payment, invitations, notification of conferences, networking letters to other COSH groups, unions, and political groups, and basic requests for information regarding health and safety issues and NYCOSH itself. VDT hazards, right to know material and workers' compensation materials, although less in bulk, are important aspects of the collection. These materials include legislation drawn up under the auspices of NYCOSH to strengthen workers' compensation in New York State and VDT guidelines in New York City. NYCOSH sponsored two "right to know" conferences and was active in lobbying for stricter legislation regarding employers' responsibility to inform workers and near by residents of the presence of toxic materials.
Take Down Policy
Archived websites are made accessible for purposes of education and research. NYU Libraries have given attribution to rights holders when possible; however, due to the nature of archival collections, we are not always able to identify this information.
If you hold the rights to materials in our archived websites that are unattributed, please let us know so that we may maintain accurate information about these materials.
If you are a rights holder and are concerned that you have found material on this website for which you have not granted permission (or is not covered by a copyright exception under US copyright laws), you may request the removal of the material from our site by submitting a notice, with the elements described below, to the special.collections@nyu.edu.
Please include the following in your notice: Identification of the material that you believe to be infringing and information sufficient to permit us to locate the material; your contact information, such as an address, telephone number, and email address; a statement that you are the owner, or authorized to act on behalf of the owner, of an exclusive right that is allegedly infringed and that you have a good-faith belief that use of the material in the manner complained of is not authorized by the copyright owner, its agent, or the law; a statement that the information in the notification is accurate and made under penalty of perjury; and your physical or electronic signature. Upon receiving a notice that includes the details listed above, we will remove the allegedly infringing material from public view while we assess the issues identified in your notice.
Freedom of information.; Correspondence.; Asbestos -- Law and legislation.; Workers' compensation -- New York (State) -- New York.; Radiation-protective agents.; Video display terminals.; Industrial hygiene -- New York (State) -- New York; Industrial safety -- New York (State) -- New York; Hazardous wastes -- Law and legislation.; Industrial accidents -- New York (State) -- New York; Poisons -- Safety measures.; Radiation -- Safety measures.; Minutes (administrative records); Occupational diseases -- New York (State) -- New York.; Beauty shop -- Law and legislation; United States. Occupational Safety and Health Administration; Shufro, Joel A., 1943-; New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health
- Series I: Management, 1977-1989
  Scope and Content Note
  Series I: Management, 1977-1989 includes the minutes of all NYCOSH committees, correspondence, technical inquiries, fund raising material, financial information, membership files, information regarding other COSH groups, nationally and internationally, and the New York State COSH.
  - NYCOSH (New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health) Minutes, 1979-1981; cuid7624 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - NYCOSH (New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health) Minutes, 1982-1983; cuid7625 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - NYCOSH (New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health) Minutes, 1984-1985; cuid7626 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - NYCOSH (New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health) Annual Meeting, 1984; cuid7627 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Health and Technical Minutes, 1980; cuid7628 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Health and Technical Minutes, 1981; cuid7629 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Health and Technical Minutes, 1981-1982; cuid7630 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Health and Technical Referral System, 1982; cuid7631 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Health and Technical Minutes, 1983-1985; cuid7632 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - NYCOSH (New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health) Personnel Committee, 1983; cuid7633 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - NYCOSH (New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health) Political Education Committee, 1981-1985; cuid7634 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Newsletter Committee, 1984-1985; cuid7635 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Workers' Compensation Minutes, Sep 6, 1983 & Dec 6, 1984; cuid7636 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Board Expansion and By-Laws Change, 1984; cuid7637 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - NYCOSH (New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health) Correspondence, Sep 28, 1978 - Jun 12, 1980; cuid7638 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - NYCOSH (New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health) Correspondence, Mar 2, 1981 - Feb 13, 1982; cuid7639 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - NYCOSH (New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health) Correspondence Outgoing, Feb 9, 1981 - Dec 24, 1981; cuid7640 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - NYCOSH (New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health) Correspondence Incoming, Jan 5, 1982 - Dec 21, 1983; cuid7641 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - NYCOSH (New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health) Correspondence Outgoing, Jan - Jun 1982; cuid7642 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - NYCOSH (New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health) Correspondence Outgoing, Jul 1, 1982 - Dec 30, 1982; cuid7643 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - NYCOSH (New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health) Correspondence Incoming, Jan 1983 - Jun 28, 1983; cuid7644 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - NYCOSH (New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health) Correspondence Incoming, Jun 3, 1983 - Dec 20, 1983; cuid7645 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - NYCOSH (New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health) Correspondence Outgoing, Jan 3, 1983 - Jun 29, 1983; cuid7646 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - NYCOSH (New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health) Correspondence Outgoing, Jun 18, 1983 - Dec 29, 1983; cuid7647 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - NYCOSH (New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health) Correspondence Incoming, Jan 6, 1984 - Apr 27, 1984; cuid7648 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - NYCOSH (New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health) Correspondence Incoming, Apr 4, 1984 - Dec 21, 1984; cuid7649 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - NYCOSH (New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health) Correspondence Outgoing, Apr 13, 1984 - Dec 27, 1984; cuid7650 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Assistance Requests, 1980; cuid7651 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Assistance Requests, 1980-1981; cuid7652 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Assistance Requests, 1982; cuid7653 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Assistance Requests, 1983; cuid7654 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Inquiries and Assistance Requests, Nov 1977 - Nov 1983; cuid7655 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 1983 Election Nominations, cuid7656 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Activities Reports, 1980 & 1983; cuid7657 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Right to Know Membership Survey, 1982; cuid7658 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - NYCOSH (New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health) Mailings, 1979-1980; cuid7659 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - NYCOSH (New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health) Finances, 1981-1985; cuid7660 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - NYCOSH (New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health) Tax Exemption, cuid7661 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - NYCOSH (New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health) Fund Raising Party Material, 1982-1984; cuid7662 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - NYCOSH (New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health) Benefit Receptions, 1982, 1984, 1985; cuid7663 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - In Kind Contributions, 1983; cuid7664 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Grant Application, 1985; cuid7665 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Grant Application, 1986; cuid7666 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Grant Application, Apr 1, 1986 - Mar 31, 1987; cuid7667 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Grant Application, 1987-1988; cuid7668 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Grant Application, 1987-1988; cuid7669 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Grant Application, 1988-1989; cuid7670 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Grant Proposal Résumés, cuid7671 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Buying a Computer, 1986; cuid7672 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - DATA SHEETS, 1977-1984; cuid7673 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Workers' Compensation Update, July 1985; cuid7674 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Health and Safety Pamphlets, 1980-1983; cuid7675 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Referral Policy, 1983; cuid7676 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - NYCOSH (New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health) Course Material, cuid7677 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - NYCOSH (New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health) Publicity Flyers, cuid7678 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Publications List, 1984; cuid7679 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Safety Rep, Jan/Feb 1987 & Sep/Oct 1987; cuid7680 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Historical NYCOSH (New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health) Articles, 1981-1984; cuid7681 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - CARP/Local 20, United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America, 1981-1982; cuid7682 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - CARP/Local 902, United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America, 1981-1985; cuid7683 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - CHEM/Local 677, International Chemical Workers Union, 1980-1982; cuid7684 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - COMM/Local 1177, Communications Workers of America, 1982-1987; cuid7685 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - DIE/Local 30, Die, Stampers and Engravers Union, 1981; cuid7686 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - FILM/Local 702, International Alliance of Theatrical Stage Employees, 1983-1987; cuid7687 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - FIRE/Local 1446, International Association of Fire Fighters, Auburn Professional Fire Fighters, 1984; cuid7688 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - GOVERN/Local 2513, American Federation of Government Employees, 1981-1983; cuid7689 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - MAIL/Local B-751, Mail & Telephone Order Clerks, 1985-1987; cuid7690 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - NEWS/Local 3, The Newspaper Guild, 1981-1987; cuid7691 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - NURSE/United Federation of Nurses and Epidemiologists, 1989; cuid7692 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - PAPER/Local 318, United Paper Workers International, 1982-1984; cuid7693 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - PAPER BOX/Local 299, Paper Box Makers Union (IPWU), 1982-1983; cuid7694 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - POSTAL/Queens Area Local, American Postal Workers Union, 1984-1987; cuid7695 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - POST POLICE/Local 1, Federation of Postal Security Police, 1980-1983; cuid7696 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - PROF ENGIN/Local 66, International Federatin of Professional and Technical Engineers, 1981-1984; cuid7697 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - PUBLIC/Local 191, Public Employees Federation AFL-CIO, 1982-1987; cuid7698 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - PUBLIC/Local 314, Public Employees Federation AFL-CIO, 1985-1987; cuid7699 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - PUBLIC/Local 326, Public Employees Federation AFL-CIO, 1985-1987; cuid7700 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - RAILC/Queens Lodge 886, Brotherhood of Railroad Carmen, 1981-1987; cuid7701 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - RAILS/Ariel Lodge 56, Brotherhood of Railway Signalmen, 1981-1986; cuid7702 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - RAILWAY/Local 3017, Brotherhood of Railway and Airline Clerks, 1981-1987; cuid7703 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - SERVICE/Local 010, AFSCME, Local 1000 CSEA/AFSCME, 1985-1987; cuid7704 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - SERVICE/Local 429, CSEA, 1985-1987; cuid7705 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - STORE/Local 2-3, United Store Workers, 1980-1987; cuid7706 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - TEACH/Local 1380, Plainedge Federation of Teachers, 1982-1985; cuid7707 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - TEACH/Local 2839, Mohawk Valley AFT, 1985-1987; cuid7708 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - TEAM/Local 10, American Commnications Association, International Brotherhood of Teamsters, 1981-1987; cuid7709 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - TEAM/Local 72, Teamsters, 1983-1984; cuid7710 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - TEAM/Local 210, International Brotherhood of Teamsters, 1981-1983; cuid7711 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - TEAM/Local 272, Garage Employees Local Union, International Brotherhood of Teamsters, 1981-1985; cuid7712 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - TRANSPORT/Local 502, TWU, cuid7713 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - WIRE/Local 222, Wire Service Guild, The Newspaper Guild, 1982-1983; cuid7714 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Union Membership Forms, 1987-1988; cuid7715 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Union Membership Solicitation, 1989; cuid7716 (Box 3, Folder 49)